Guide to the Rutherfurd Collection 1642-1845 MS 531
New-York Historical Society
Rutherfurd collection
1642-1845 (bulk, 1721-1798)
New-York Historical Society
Alexander, James, 1691-1756
Alexander, William, 1726-1783
Rutherfurd, John, 1760-1840
Rutherfurd, Walter, 1723-1804
MS 531
13.3 Linear feet 11 document boxes on 3 microfilm reels and 21 volumes.
The Rutherfurd Collection contains material created by or pertaining to members of the Rutherfurd and Alexander families of New York City and New Jersey. The collection is primarily composed of official and private correspondence pertaining to business affairs, political affairs, land disputes, and military activities.
Scope and Content Note
The Rutherfurd Collection is composed of correspondence, maps, printed items, and miscellaneous manuscripts, circa 1710-1803, that pertain to the Alexander and Rutherfurd families. The papers of James Alexander (b.1726-d.1783), his son William Alexander (b.1726-d.1783), Walter Rutherfurd (b.1723-d.1804), and the latter's son, John Rutherfurd (b.1760-d.1840) are heavily represented in this collection.
The material pertaining to James Alexander include his correspondence with important colonial figures such as Robert Hunter, Cadwallader Colden, John Montgomerie, Lewis Morris (b.1671-d.1746), Lewis Morris, Jr., William Burnet, William Smith (b.1697-d.1769), Vincent Mathews, Philip Livingston, Peter Collinson, Robert Hunter Morris, and others. The letters concern such matters as Alexander's handling of ex-Governor Hunter's private affairs in New York, his own law practice, land purchases, sales, and disputes in New York and New Jersey, Lewis Morris's mission to London, charges against governors and other officials of New York, activities of agents in London, negotiations in England about New Jersey affairs, salary disputes, the defense of John Peter Zenger, elections in New York, the sale of Indian lands at Ticonderoga, the partition line between the Eastern and Western Divisions of New Jersey, the New Jersey land riots of the late 1740s and 1750s, and other affairs in New York.
The William Alexander papers relate mostly to his activities and interests as a contractor of supplies for the army during the French and Indian War, including correspondence with Peter Van Brugh Livingston, General William Shirley, Major John Rutherfurd, John Brainerd, Elihu Spencer, and others. The letters also relate to such matters as the defense of Oswego, construction of vessels there, the raising and transportation of troops and supplies, the Crown Point expedition in 1759, and the siege of Detroit in 1763.
The Walter Rutherfurd correspondence includes 12 letters from his nephew, John Rutherfurd, who wrote about his experiences as a subaltern in Col. Henry Bouquet's expedition to Fort Pitt during Pontiac's War, and letters from his brother, Baron Robert Rutherfurd (b.1719-d.1794), written during 1756-1794, from Leghorn, Italy, where he engaged in the mercantile business until 1777, then from London, his estate near Kelso and Edinburgh, in Scotland. He writes about life in Italy, family matters, the 1764 famine in Italy, European and American affairs, and commerce between Leghorn and America, particularly New York, where Walter was engaged in trade. Included in this part of the collection are letters from Walter to his son, John, during 1783-1803, written from New York City and the family estate, Edgerston, in New Jersey. He writes of their business affairs, particularly their New Jersey lands, friends and relations, family matters, and gives the current news about politics, prominent persons, and local events.
Arrangement
The Rutherfurd Collection is organized into three series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1642-1845 (bulk 1734-1794)
Series II: Scrapbooks, 1642-1794
Series III: Genealogy, Printed Material, and Account Book, 1650-1939
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. The collection has been microfilmed and will be brought to the researcher in that format. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Biographical / Historical
James Alexander (1691-1756) was a prominant New York statesman and lawyer. Born in Scotland on May 27, 1691, he arrived in New York in 1715 after being appointed to the position of General Surveyer of New Jersey. He married Mary Spratt Provoost (1693-1760), the widow of Samuel Provoost (d. 1719) and a merchant, on June 5, 1721. During this time, Alexander was admitted to the provincial bar and served consecutively as Attorney General in New York and New Jersey. In his later years, he continued to be active in New York politics, raised funds for Kings College, and was a founding member of the American Philosphical Society in Philadelphia. He died in New York on April 2, 1756.
William Alexander was born to James Alexander and Mary Spratt Alexander in 1726. Taking the family title of Lord Stirling, William Alexander would go on to have a successful military career. During the French and Indian War, he was responsible for supplying General Shirley's 1755 expedition to Oswego, NY. William Alexander married Sarah Livingston in 1748 and was active in his family's businesses. In the years leading up to the American Revolution, Alexander began to oppose and rebel against the Crown. His military experience earned him a commission as Brigadier General in 1776. He remained a key figure for the duration of the war and died on January 15, 1783.
Walter Rutherfurd (1723-1804) was born in Scotland to Sir John and Elizabeth Rutherfurd. He arrived in America in 1758 to serve in the French and Indian War with the Royal American Regiment. As a reward for his service, he was granted land in the Province of New Jersey. His marriage to Catherine Alexander, daughter of James Alexander, brought him property holdings in New York. With the help of his connections back in Europe, he went into importng goods and became one of the wealthiest citizens in New York. He helped found the New York Hospital (today New York-Presbyterian Hospital), the Tontine Coffee House, and the St. Andrew's Society of the State of New York. He died in New York City on January 10, 1804.
John Rutherfurd (1760-1840) was born in New York City to Walter and Catherine Alexander Rutherfurd. Like his father and maternal grandfather, he went into politics and worked as a land surveyer. Rutherfurd served a role in the New Jersey General Assembly before representing the state as a Federalist in the United States Senate from 1791 to 1798. He eventually settled with his family in New Jersey. His property was incorporated into the town of Rutherford, NJ, which is named in his honor. John Rutherfurd died in New Jersey on February 23, 1840.
Courts -- New York (State); Families -- New York (State); Landowners; Landowners -- New Jersey; Real property -- New Jersey.; Real property -- New York (State).; England -- Description and travel; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; New York (State) -- Social life and customs.; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763.; United States -- Politics and government.; Land grants; Letters (correspondence); Scrapbooks.; Trials -- New York (State).
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents, 1642-1845 (bulk 1734-1796)
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains letters of correspondence from various members of the Alexander and Rutherfurd families. Primary correspondents include James Alexander, William Alexander, Walter Rutherfurd, John Rutherfurd, Cadwallader Colden, Lewis Morris, and Peter Collinson.
  Arrangement
  The contents of Series I were originally bound into six volumes and are arranged by their original order by volume. The page number is indicated in brackets. The volumes of Subseries I.A include a table of contents and transcriptions that correspond to the six volumes and have been kept in their original order.
  Series I is available on microfilm.
  - Subseries I.A: Table of Contents and Transcriptions, Undated
    Two sets of Contents for Albums 1-4 of the Rutherfurd Collection. There is an entry for each page in the albums describing the document / correspondence, etc. on that page. Some of the entries are lengthy and may include transcription from the document; others are brief. The two sets are almost identical although one has, at the end of its fourth volume, a Table of Contents for albums 1-4 that consists of a one-line entry for each page. Volumes 9-12 include word-for-word transcriptions of portions of the Rutherfurd Collection correspondence.
    - Table of Contents Set 1, Volume 1 (Volume 1)
    - Table of Contents Set 1, Volume 2 (Volume 2)
    - Table of Contents Set 1, Volume 3 (Volume 3)
    - Table of Contents Set 1, Volume 4 (Volume 4)
    - Table of Contents Set 2, Volume 1 (Volume 5)
    - Table of Contents Set 2, Volume 2 (Volume 6)
    - Table of Contents Set 2, Volume 3 (Volume 7)
    - Table of Contents Set 2, Volume 4 (Volume 8)
    - Transcriptions for Volume 1 (Volume 9)
    - Transcriptions for Volume 2 (Volume 10)
    - Transcriptions for Volume 3 (Volume 11)
    - Transcriptions for Volume 4 (Volume 12)
  - Subseries I.B: Volume I, 1675-1733
    SCOPE / CONTENT NOTE TBD
    - [1] Newark Daily Advertiser - Resolutions of N.J. Historical Society upon presentation of "Stirling" papers by Mr. Duer, 1845 May 10
    - [1] Map of NY, NJ, and CT, 1675
    - [1] Note taken from a large folio, Undated
    - [2] List of payments, 1705 May
    - [3] Acknowledgement of Non Commissioned Officers of Weems' Indian Company, 1705
    - [3] Route to Hot Spring in Virginia from Philadelphia, Undated
    - [3] Minutes, Undated
    - [4] Augusta Court House, Virginia to Castle, Delaware, Undated
    - [5] Letter from Lords of Trade to Gov. Hunter, N.Y., 1711 November 13
    - [6] Names of German families settled on Hudson River, Undated
    - [7] Letter of Lords of Trade to Gov. Robert Hunter, 1712 June 12
    - [9] Inventory of Articles belonging to James Alexander, 1715 October 15
    - [11] Address to the Lords Committee from N.Y. Council and General Assembly, 1718 July 2
    - [13] Address to Governor Hunter by General Assembly, N.Y., 1719 April 30
    - [15] Address to Governor Hunter from General Assembly, N.Y., 1718 October 14
    - [17] Letter from Lewis Morris to James Alexander, 1721 January 18
    - [19] Westchester, Deposition of William Morass, regarding a prisoner in jail, 1721 August 19
    - [20] Power of Attorney from Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1721 November 1
    - [21] R. Amber, 1721 April 29
    - [21] Letter from Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1721 September 6
    - [21] Letter from Charles Dunster to James Alexander, 1721 September 10
    - [21] Letter from J. Hunter, 1722 February 6
    - [22] Letter from Archibald Kennedy to Charles Dunster, 1722 November 22
    - [23] Letter to Charles Dunster, 1722 February 10
    - [23] Warrant from Governor Burnet to Attorney General James Alexander, 1722 August 1
    - [23] Warrant from Commissioner Governor William Burnet, Secretary George Clarke, and Cadwallader Colden, Undated
    - [24] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 May 12
    - [25] Report of Committee of the Council [Fort George] to the Governor, 1722 December 1
    - [26] Report of Committee from the Council [Fort George] to Governor Burnet, 1723 February 7
    - [27] Acknowledgement from the Citizens of Harlem for Satisfaction, 1723 July 10
    - [28] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1723 August 9
    - [28] Letter supposed to be from William Penn to James Alexander, 1723 November 2
    - [28] Letter, 1724 August 9
    - [29] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1725 January 19
    - [31] Letter to Colonel Kooper, 1725 October 31
    - [32] William Smith with seal, 1725 April 2
    - [32] Mr. Sonmam's bond to Charles Hay, Undated
    - [33] Copy of Obligation from Peter Sonmam to Charles Hay, Undated
    - [33] P. Jonnans, 1724 March 25
    - [34] Anne Hamilton to James Alexander, 1725 April 9
    - [34] Letter from Clem Plumsted to James Alexander, 1726 July 11
    - [35] Letter from Andrew Hamilton to James Alexander, 1726 August 25
    - [37] Instructions, 1727 March 23
    - [37] Additional instructions from William Smith, Attorney, to James Alexander, 1727 July 21
    - [38] Letter from William Smith, Attorney, to James Alexander, 1727 July 21
    - [39] Communication from Governor William Burnet to Surveyor General Cadwallader Colden, 1722 December 16
    - [41] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1727 July 21
    - [41] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1727 July 21
    - [43] Ata committee... piece, 1727 November 27
    - [43] Deposition of Robert Livingston, Garret Van Horn, etc., 1727 December 1
    - [45] Letter, 1728 January 1
    - [45] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to Governor Burnet, 1723 September 2
    - [45] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1728 February 10
    - [47] Vindication of Governor Burnet by Cadwallader Colden, Undated
    - [47] G. William, Undated
    - [48] Abel Copperthwaites' Note and Dialogue enclosed to James Alexander, Undated
    - [48] A ferry-house dialogue of which Mr. A. Phillipse is the subject, Undated
    - [49] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 May 17
    - [51] Draught of letter from James Alexander to Colonel Lewis Morris, Undated
    - [51] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 June 1
    - [53] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 June 21
    - [53] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 June 30
    - [55] Letter from William Sinclair to James Alexander, 1728 July 4
    - [55] Letter from Ex-Governor Hunter to James Alexander, 1728 August 10
    - [57] Memorial drafted by James Alexander to Governor Montgomerie, 1728 August 17
    - [59] Letter from a Gentleman in the city to a friend in the country, 1728 October 22
    - [61] Letter addressed to Governor Montgomerie by Robert Walker and others, written by James Alexander, 1728 August 30
    - [63] Origin of dispute with Governor Burnet, by Cadwallader Colden, Undated
    - [63] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to Governor Montgomerie, 1728 August 31
    - [65] May it Please your Excellency, Undated
    - [67] Amount it will be Easy, Undated
    - [69] Draught of "thirteen reasons" by James Alexander, 1728 August 31
    - [71] Letter from James Alexander to Governor Montgomerie, 1728 September 1
    - [73] Letter from Lewis Morris, Jr. to James Alexander, Undated
    - [73] I must beg leave..., 1728 September 12
    - [75] An address to Governor Montgomerie drafter by James Alexander and signed by Several others, Undated
    - [75] Duplicate of I must be Leave..., Undated
    - [77] Letter from James Alexander to Governor Montgomerie, 1728 September 4
    - [79] Copy of "four" instead of the "thirteen reasons," by James Alexander, 1728 September 4
    - [81] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 September 6
    - [83] Draft of Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, Undated
    - [85] Deliberations of James Alexander submitted to Governor Montgomerie, Undated
    - [87] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, Undated
    - [89] Draft of letter to "Bradford the printer" from fictitious correspondent, 1728 September 25
    - [91] Draft of letter designed for Lords of Trade, by James Alexander, but withdrawn, Undated
    - [91] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 November 8
    - [91] Tho we make no doubt..., 1728 October 29
    - [91] Copy of a letter, Undated
    - [91] Draught letter, 1728 August 29
    - [93] Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 November 19
    - [93] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1728 November 29
    - [95] Draft of a Letter from James Alexander to Ex-Governor Hunter, 1728 November 20
    - [95] May it please... as to that, Undated
    - [97] Letter from James Alexander to Cadwallader Colden, 1728 November 25
    - [99] Letter from Lewis Morris, Jr. to James Alexander, 1728 December 12
    - [99] Letter from Governor William Burnet to James Alexander, 1728 December 16
    - [101] Draft of letter from one to another gentleman of the council, 1728 December 20
    - [103] were to..., Undated
    - [105] Letter from Lewis Morris, Jr. to James Alexander, 1729 January
    - [105] A treatise upon the teachings of Reason and Experience, Undated
    - [107] Letter from James Alexander to Governor William Burnet, 1729 February 10
    - [109] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 February 4
    - [109] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 March 4
    - [111] Being this moment..., 1729 March 28
    - [111] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, Undated
    - [111] Letter from Lewis Morris to James Alexander, 1729 March 9
    - [111] Draft of letter from James Alexander to Governor Montgomerie, 1729 March 10
    - [113] Letter in Dutch from Philip Livingston to Mr. Van Hoorn, Undated
    - [113] Letter from Lewis Morris to James Alexander, 1729 March 29
    - [115] Deed to tract of land in Albany Country from certain Indians to Van Hoorn and others, 1729 May 2
    - [116] Interesting letter without address or signatures, dated London, 1729 March 25
    - [117] Letter from Lewis Morris to James Alexander, 1729 March 21
    - [117] Letter from Governor William Burnet to James Alexander, 1729 March 31
    - [117] London - I have nothing, 1729 March 25
    - [117] Letter from Lewis Morris to James Alexander, 1729 March 31
    - [119] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 May 20
    - [119] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 May 27
    - [119] Coldenham - Cadwallader Colden, 1729 May 10
    - [121] Letter from Governor William Burnet to James Alexander, 1729 June 2
    - [121] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 June 14
    - [123] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Cadwallader Colden, 1729 June 18
    - [125] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 July 13
    - [125] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Cadwallader Colden, 1729 June 28
    - [125] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 June 22
    - [127] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 July 13
    - [127] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1729 July 15
    - [128] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Governor William Burnet, 1729 January 27
    - [129] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Governor William Burnet, 1729 July 28
    - [131] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 August 4
    - [131] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1729 August 29
    - [133] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Ex-Governor Robert Hunter, 1723 February 3
    - [133] Draft of a letter about Dissertation on "Liberty and Necessity" by James Alexander, 1730 March 2
    - [135] Draft of a letter from James Alexander probably to Mr. Paris, 1730 May 11
    - [135] The appeal of..., 1730 May 17
    - [139] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Mr. Paris, 1730 December 22
    - [141] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to David Barclay, 1731 January 1
    - [141] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Mr. Paris, 1731 January 18
    - [141] Also if any..., 1730 May 11
    - [143] Copy of address to the Board of Trade, 1731 May 27
    - [144] Duplicate copy of His Majesty's Order, 1731 August 12
    - [145] Letter from Philip Livingston to Messrs. Van Hoorn and Provoost, 1731 June 28
    - [147] Letter from Josh Miln to James Alexander, 1731 May 26
    - [147] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Josh Miln, 1731 July 19
    - [147] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1731 July 7
    - [149] Letter and Invoice from Thomas Penn to James Alexander, 1732 January 18
    - [149] Letter to Mr. Paris, 1731 September 13
    - [149] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Mr. Paris, 1731 September 18
    - [149] Invoice of Goods, 1732 April 20
    - [151] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Ex-Governor Robert Hunter, 1732 February 7
    - [151] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1732 June 13
    - [153] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1732 August 18
    - [153] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1732 September 9
    - [155] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Ex-Governor Robert Hunter, 1732 September 20
    - [155] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1732 October 10
    - [155] Letter from Ex-Governor Hunter to James Alexander, 1732 October 18
    - [157] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1732 November 22
    - [157] Letter from William Smith to Colonel Lewis Morris, 1733 January 2
    - [157] Proclamation by Governor William Cosby, 1733 February 19
    - [159] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Mr. Paris, 1733 March
    - [161] Letter from Ex-Governor Robert Hunter to James Alexander, 1733 August 27
    - [163] Letter from James Alexander to Ex-Governor Robert Hunter, 1733 November 8
    - [164] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Ex-Governor Robert Hunter, 1733 November 8
    - [165] An estimate of the Value of Ex-Governor Hunter's property in the Provinces, 1733 November 8
    - [167] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Mr. Pople, 1733 December 4
    - [168] Letter from D. Clarkson to James Alexander, 1733 December 4
    - [169] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Alderman Perry, 1733 December 4
    - [171] J. Minander, 1733 December 15
    - [171] Draft of a letter from James Alexander to Colonel Lewis Morris, 1733 December 15
    - [173] Letter from Colonel Lewis Morris to James Alexander, 1733 December
    - [175] Affidavit of Hugh Munro, Lieutenant of Indian Co. Fusiliers, 1733 December 17
    - [175] Hugh Morris..., 1733 December 18
    - [177] Letter from D. Clarkson to James Alexander, 1734 January 2
    - [178] Letter from John De Witt to James Alexander, 1734 January 2
    - [179] The Governeur continues, Undated
    - [181] Letter from Thomas Penn to James Alexander, 1734 January 14
    - [181] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1734 January 24
    - [181] Letter from Cadwallader Colden to James Alexander, 1734 January 27
    - [183] Copy of a printed letter from James Jackson to a friend in Ireland, 1734 April 10
    - [185] Vindication of James Alexander and William Smith, 1734 April 9
    - [187] Vindication p. 5-8, 1734 April 9
    - [189] Vindication p. 9-12, 1734 April 9
    - [189] Directed to my wife, 1734 February 7
    - [191] Hand did I say..., 1734 February 7
    - [193] Vindication p. 13-16, 1734 April 9
    - [195] Vindication p. 17-20, 1734 April 9
    - [197] George the Second..., 1733 February 17
    - [197] Copy of the commission of Judge Phillipse from His Majesty, 1733 August 21
    - [197] Copy of Summons to Rip Van Dam to appear to answer, 1733 February 19
    - [199] Memorandum of Enquiries to be submitted to Com. on Adm. of Justice, Undated
    - [201] Memorandum of Enquiries to be submitted to Com. for Courts of Justice, Undated
  - Subseries I.C: Volume II, 1734-1742
    Much of the material in Subseries I.C pertains to the 1734 trial of John Peter Zenger (1697-1746), a German-born printer and journalist, on the charge of libel. Although he was ultimately acquited, the trial would be one of the earliest cases concerning freedom of the press.
    - [1] Letter from Messrs. James Alexander & William Smith to Colonel Lewis Morris, 1734 June 11
    - [1] Letter from Joseph Country to John Peter Zenger, publisher of "Journal", 1734 June 14